Hello, welcome back to our course, and today we are going to continue talking about Programming in R.
So let us look at if-else statements.
So if-else statements check whether a specific condition applies. So, for example, here, we have the simple IF.
Statement. So, we first define X, Which is 1, and then
if X is 2, then we should print X equals 2. Now, clearly, here, our X is not 2.
Now, an if-else statement. So, once again, X is 1, and then
if X is 2, we should print X equals 2.
Else, so if X is not 2, then we print X is not equal 2, and then, indeed, you can see that
in the second case, we have something printed, because we told R to print something if the condition is not satisfied.
Here, we have more elaborate if-else statement.
So, here, our X is 1, and then we say if X is 3, then print
X is 3, else if X is 2, then print X is 2,
else print that X is not 3, and X is not 2, and you can see that since X is 1,
we have the third option printed. Then we have this function ifelse, and this function returns a value depending on the condition.
So it works like if in Excel. So here, we have this simple example, X is 1.
So now we check ifelse X is larger or equals 0,
then print X. Otherwise, print the absolute value of X.
So, for example, here we could use it to catch negative values for square roots. So, for example, here we define this X as a vector from 2 to minus 1.
And then, you can see here that we apply it inside of a square root function, so inside we have ifelse().
So you can see here that if X is larger than 0, then we indeed apply this square root,
but if X is smaller than 0, then it should return us NA, so not available. And indeed, you can see that
We computed the square root for 2, for 1, for 0, but not for - 1.
we can also apply a switch function, so switch avoids long if-else constructs.
And, it can take a numeric value or a string as expression.
And it checks it against different cases. For example, we have a function rootsquare, and then this is a function of two parameters.
X and type, and then basically. Inside, we have a switch. So what does it do?
It checks the type, and then if we insert there 1,
then our function would square our parameter. If we insert as type 2, then our function would
take a square root of our parameter. And here, let us call our function, so we can see that rootsquare(10,type), and then I passed 1. So 1 refers to the first statement in our switch.
So indeed, I have as an output a square of 10.
Now, if I pass 10 and 2, this refers to the second
element in our switch. And indeed, I get a square root of 10.
If type is a string, R matches the string in a switch.
So here we define the function center. Once again, with two parameters, X and type.
And then you can see that here we have switch. And it switches between different types. So, for example, we can have a type mean,
it computes a mean, median, it computes the median, and trimmed mean,
it computes a trimmed mean. And indeed, here, you can see that I defined vector X,
and type, as a type = mean, then indeed I get a mean.
And here, if I pass X to center(), and
If I type median, then it matches median. And if I type trimmed, it matches the third element, trimmed.
Now, let us talk briefly about for loops. Often, you will want to call a function iteratively for different values. So, for example,
here imagine that I would like to print i's from 1 to 4.
So, for example, for I in 1 to 4, so I need to define
the index inside my sequence of numbers.
I would like to print i and you can see that I have all i's from 1 to 4 printed.
Here, another example: I define my index, and then in letters().
For letters from 1 to 4, I would like to print the index, and indeed, here you can see that I print all the four letters.
I could also generate a vector containing 0's of length 400 using a for loop.
So here, I define this empty vector, so numeric with
only zeros. And then I would like to fill it with.
1 to 400. So how can I do it using for loop? So basically,
for i, so the index i in 1 to 400. What do I do?
I fill each element, each i'th from 1 to 400 of my vector A with I, so with 1 to 400.
And indeed, I will create a vector filled with 1 to 400.
But this for loop takes much longer than just simply defining it
as A equals 1 to 400. So, indeed, this can be helpful, but sometimes,
faster alternatives exist. Now let us briefly talk about while loops. So, while loops allow to perform an operation until a logical operation evaluates to TRUE.
If you make a mistake, you get an infinite loop. So here we have i,
which is now set to 0, and I would like to continue
my operation until i is smaller than 4. So basically here, while i is smaller than 4, I would like to
assign to i i plus 1, and this can be handy in other programming tasks, so yeah, so don't forget that.
And I would like to print i. So, i is 0, okay.
So, inside the while loop, I'm redefining i. So i was 0, 0 plus 1 is 1, and they printed it.
Now, i is 1, 1 plus 1 is 2, I printed it. Now, i is 2, 2 plus 1 is i, I print it.
Now, i is 3, 3 plus 1 is 4. This is 4, and then we said that
we would stop, while i is smaller than 4. So basically, I stopped at 3 and I printed the result, and that's it.
There is also a repeat loop in R. And repeat starts an unconditional loop.
It doesn't check a condition for you, and you must test a condition inside the loop and break explicitly to exit,
unlike while, with checks before each iteration. So here, look what's happening right now. So, I'm defining my i, which is 0, and then I repeat
the printing, so I repeat redefining i's.
And then I break this loop only if
I define this break statement. So, break exits a loop. So basically, I repeat the statement inside the repeat loop, and then,
I'm printing the i, and then I need to define a break statement to exit the loop. So we can see that
I print the first, the second, the third, the fourth element, and then if I is equal to 4, we just print We are done, so we can break this loop. Thank you!.